<tool id="GWASwithEMMAX_Step3" name="GWAS with EMMAX. Step 3: Kinship matrix" version="0.1.0">
    <requirements>
        
    </requirements>
    <command detect_errors="exit_code"><![CDATA[
        emmax-kin-intel64 -v -d 10 '$SNPLD02' > SNPLD0.2.aBN.kinf
    ]]></command>
    <inputs>
        <param type="data" name="SNPLD02" format="tped" label="Genotype file containing the SNPs filtered by LD in tped format (output from the Step 2)" />
    </inputs>
    <outputs>
        <data label="GWASwithEMMAX_Step3: Kinship matrix" name="SNPLD0.2.aBN.kinf" from_work_dir="SNPLD0.2.aBN.kinf" />
    </outputs>
    <help><![CDATA[
       This GWAS pipeline performs association mapping using the EMMAX software, a mixed model accounting for the sample structure. In addition to the computational efficiency obtained by EMMA algorithm, EMMAX takes advantage of the fact that each loci explains only a small fraction of complex traits, which allows us to avoid repetitive variance component estimation procedure, resulting in a significant amount of increase in computational time of association mapping using mixed model.
       EMMAX is a linear mixed model (LMM) to perform GWAS, correcting by a wide range of sample structures (which encompasses population stratification and hidden relatedness). To this end, it uses an internally calculated kinship matrix as a random effect, and population structure externally calculated as a fixed effect
       This is the third step of the workflow, which calculates the kinkship matrix, needed to correct for kinship during the association mapping analysis.
       This tool requires a tped file as input file, containing the SNPs

       *EMMAX* program is used to perform this step.

       
    ]]></help>
    <citations>
        <citation type="bibtex">
@misc{githublink,
  author = {Danecek, Petr et al},
  year = {2011},
  title = {The Variant Call Format and VCFtools},
  publisher = {},
  journal = {Bioinformatics},
  url = {https://vcftools.github.io/license.html},
}</citation>
    </citations>
</tool>